now we're going to do a slightly more
detailed directory example to show how
the directory doesn't become a
bottleneck when a bus would here we have
four cores each with its own cache and
also next to each core is a slice of the
directory let's assume that each slice
just keeps track of one block so this is
the directory slice where we keep the
block X information and then next to
cach one there is directory y z and w
and now let's assume that the core zero
right X at about the same time where
core one is trying to read why this is a
cach miss and we send the request to the
directory that is the home for X which
happens to be our own nearby slice of
the directory when we read y we go to
our own slice let's say that cach 2 also
reads Y at about the same time so what
happens now is the right to X and the
read to Y here are probably going to be
processed at about the same time
completely independently by these
directories meanwhile the read Y is
traveling through the network to this
directory in each of these directories
we see that the block is not present in
any of the caches so we allow exclusive
access for the read and here of course
the block will be modified anyway so
here we will set the Dirty Bit And note
that block X is now in the cache zero
and here we will set the dirty bit
because exclusive can become dir easily
and set the presence bit for cache one
now the read Y is traveling to this
directory let's say that cach one is
being accessed with a right tox and it's
a cach miss so it gets sent to this
directory so this will probably arrive
here first we will check the presence
vector and the dirtiness information and
see that cach one is the one that has
the data and that it might be dirty
there so we forward the request to read
to cach one cach one acknowledges that
request changes its state to Shared we
get the response that doesn't carry data
so now we know that the block was not
dirty and we change it to not dirty we
then get the data and forward it to cach
two and now we note also that cach 2
might have the data and the cache to
eventually will get the data so it will
eventually get the shared State and the
block y meanwhile the right X is getting
here and because we need to write we're
going to send an invalidation and an
external write request to Cache zero so
here the cache needs to respond with the
data and because it's a right request it
sets a state to invalid and responds
with the data this is also a right so
the block block will remain dirty but
now the directory knows that cach Z no
longer has the data and we send the data
to cach one so now the Cashman will
eventually get the data in the modified
State and as you can see the right to X
and the read to Y are largely proceeding
independent of each other except for
maybe possible connection in the network
so if our network is good and has many
different paths between these caches and
directories then really there was no
point where these requests competed with
each other for anything this one was
processed by this cache and this
directory this one was processed by this
cache and this directory and we involved
other caches if necessary but in this
case it was this cach so these requests
were still largely independent now let's
say we want to write to Y on in this
cache this will be sent to the directory
for y so the message travels over here
the directory for y now sees that caches
one and two might have the data and that
none of them are dirty so it just sends
the invalidation request to caches one
and two when they receive this
invalidate the block Y and send back
responses that indicate that they have
done so when the First Response arise
from let's say cach one the directory
eliminates this bit when the second
response comes in the directory
eliminates this bit now that we know
there are no more remaining sharers we
can send the data to the requesting
writer and note that it's going to have
the block and that the block will be
dirty so now we send the block over here
and this block becomes modified here and
so on so again this right only involved
the caches and the directory entry that
actually needed to be involved for this
block this cash and directory for
example were completely operating
independently of this and these two
directories could have done something
else